So again, I'm very happy
to have Jason here.
So he's an AI researcher
based in San Francisco,
currently working at OpenAI.
He was previously a
research scientist
at Google Brain, where he
popularized key ideas in LLMS
such as chain of thought
prompting, instruction tuning,
as well as emergent phenomena.
He's also a good
friend of mine and he's
been here before
to give some talks,
so we're very happy to have you
back, Jason, and take it away.
Great.
[APPLAUSE]
Well, yeah, thanks
for the intro.
So a bit about the structure.
So I'll talk for
around 30 minutes,
and then I'll take
a few questions,
and then Kyeong Hwan
will talk for 30 minutes,
and then we'll both take
questions at the end.
Great.
So I want to talk about
a few very basic things.
And I think the fundamental
question that I hope to get at
is, why do language
models work so well?
And one thing that
I encourage everyone
to do that I found to be
extremely helpful in trying
to answer this question
is to use a tool which
is manually inspect data.
And I'll give a short anecdote.
I've been doing this
for a long time.
So in 2019, I was trying to
build one of the first lung
cancer classifiers, so
there would be an image,
and you have to say like,
OK, what type of lung cancer
is this?
And my first thing
was like, OK, if I
want to train a neural
network to do this,
I should be able to,
at least, do the task.
So I went to my
advisor and I said
like, oh, I want to learn
to do this task first.
And he said, Jason, you
need a medical degree
and like three
years of pathology
experience to even do this task.
And I found that a
bit discouraging,
but I went and did it anyways.
So I basically looked at the
specific type of lung cancer
that I was working on.
And I'd read all the papers on
how to classify different types.
And I went to pathologists
and I said, OK, I
try to classify these,
what do I do wrong?
And then, what do
you think of that?
And in the end, I learned how to
do this task of classifying lung
cancer.
And the result of this
was, I gained intuitions
about the task that
led to many papers.
OK.
So first, I will do a quick
review of language models.
So the way language models are
trained are with the next word
prediction task.
So let's say you
have a sentence,
Dartmouth students like to--
and the goal of
next word prediction
is, you have some
words that come before,
and then you want to
predict the next word.
And what the language
model does is
it outputs a probability
for every single word
in the vocabulary.
So vocabulary would be like,
a aardvark, drink, study,
and then all the
way to zucchini.
And then the language
model is going
to put a probability over
every single word here.
So the probability of
a being the next word
is something really small.
Aardvark is something
really small.
And then maybe drink is
like say, 0.6, study is 0.3,
zucchini is, again,
really small.
And then the way that you
train the language model is
you say, I want-- let's say
drink is the correct word here,
I want this number here, 0.6,
to be as close as possible to 1.
So your loss is basically
how close is the actual word?
The probability of
the actual next word?
And you want this loss
to be as low as possible.
OK.
So the first intuition that I
would encourage everyone to use
is, next word prediction is,
massively multi-task learning.
And what I mean by
this is the following,
I'll give a few examples.
So when you train
a language model
on a large enough database,
a large enough data set
on this task of next
word prediction,
you have a lot of sentences
that you can learn from.
So for example, there might be
some sentence, in my free time
I like to-- and
the language model
has to learn that code should be
higher probability than the word
banana, so it
learns some grammar.
It will learn lexical
semantics, so somewhere
in your data set there might be
a sentence, I went to the store
to buy papaya,
dragonfruit, and durian.
And the language
model should know
that the probability of durian
should be higher than squirrel.
The language model will
learn world knowledge.
So there will be some sentence
on the internet that says,
the capital of
Azerbaijan is-- and then
the language model should
learn that it should
be Baku instead of London.
You can learn traditional NLP
tasks like sentiment analysis.
So there will be
some sentence, I
was engaged on the
edge of my seat
the whole time the movie was.
And the language
model looks like, OK,
if these are the
prior next words,
the next word should
probably be good and not bad.
And then finally-- or another
example is translation.
So here, you might
see some sentence.
The word for pretty
and Spanish is--
and then the
language model should
weigh bonita more than ola.
Spatial reasoning.
So you might even
have some sentence
like, Iroh went to the
kitchen to make some tea.
Standing next to Iroh,
Zuko pondered his destiny.
Zuko left the-- and
then kitchen should be
higher probability than store.
And then finally, even
some math questions.
So you might have some
arithmetic exam answer key
somewhere on the internet,
and then the language model
looks at this and says, OK,
the next word should probably
be 15 and not 11.
And you can have basically
millions of tasks like this
when you have a huge data set.
And you can think of this as
basically extreme multitask
learning.
And these are sort of very
clean examples of tasks,
but I'll give an example of how
arbitrary some of these tasks
can be.
So here's a sentence
from Wikipedia.
Biden married Neilia.
OK, and then now, pretend
you're the language model.
And you could say, OK,
what's the next word here?
And the next word
here is hunter.
So it's Biden's
first wife, and so,
OK, what's the
language model learning
to predict from
predicting this word,
I guess like world knowledge.
And then what's the
next word after this?
It turns out the
next word is a comma.
So here the model is learning,
basically, comma prediction.
And then what's the
next word after that?
I think it's kind of hard to
know, but the answer is a.
And I guess this is
like maybe grammar,
but like somewhat arbitrary.
And then what's the
next word after that?
It turns out it's student.
And this I would
say, I don't know
what task this is, this is
it could have been woman,
it could have been
something else,
so this is like a
pretty arbitrary task.
And the point that I'm
trying to make here
is that, the next
word prediction
task is really challenging.
So if you do this over
the entire database
you're going to
learn a lot of tasks.
OK.
The next intuition
I want to talk about
is scaling, which is, by the
way, say scaling compute.
And by the way, compute
is equal to how much data
you have times the size
of the language model.
Reliably improves loss.
And this idea was
basically pioneered
by Kaplan et Al in 2020.
I would encourage you
guys to read the paper.
And what this basically says
is, you can have a plot here,
and we'll see many
plots like this,
where the x-axis is compute,
and the y-axis is loss.
And what this intuition says
is, you can train one language
model, you'll have that loss.
And obviously, you
want loss to be lower,
so you can train the next
one, it'll have that loss.
If you train the one after
that, it'll have that loss,
then if you train the one after
that, we'll have that loss.
And you can basically predict
the loss of a language model
based on how much compute
you're going to use to train it.
And the reason why
this is called a law
is that in this paper they
showed that the x-axis here
is actually seven
orders of magnitude.
So basically, it
would be surprising
if the trend broke
if you continued.
And the important
thing about this
is that the line does
not go like that,
because if it went like
that, then it would saturate,
and then putting more compute or
training a larger language model
wouldn't actually
lead to lower loss.
OK, so I think a question that
we don't have a good answer
to as a field, but I'll give
you like a handwavy answer is,
why does scaling up the
size of your language model
improve the loss?
And I'll give like two
basically hand-wavy answers.
So here's a small LM,
and here's large LM.
So one thing that's important
is, how good is your language
model at memorizing facts?
And imagine you're a
small language model,
and you see a bunch of
facts on the internet.
You have to be pretty
choosy in which facts
you memorize because if you
don't have that many parameters,
you're like, oh, I can only
memorize a million facts,
is this one of the
facts that I want
to memorize at the lowest loss?
And so you have to
be very selective.
Whereas if you're a
large language model,
you can memorize a
lot of tail knowledge.
And so basically, every fact
you see, you don't have to say,
is this something
I want to memorize?
You can just memorize it.
And then the other
hand-wavy answer I'll give
is small language models tend
to learn first order heuristics.
So if you're like a
small language model,
you're like already struggling
to get the grammar correct,
you're not going to do your
best to try to get the math
problem exactly correct.
Whereas if you're a
large language model,
you have a lot of parameters
in your forward pass,
and you can try to do
really complicated things
to get the next token correct,
and to get the loss as
low as possible.
OK, so the third
intuition I'll talk about
is, while overall,
loss improves smoothly,
individual tasks can
improve suddenly.
And here's what I mean by this.
So you can write
your overall loss.
By this I mean, if you
take some corpus of data
and you compute the overall loss
on every word in that data set,
the overall loss because we know
that next word prediction is
massively multitask
learning, you
can decompose this
overall loss into the loss
of every single individual task.
So you have, I don't
know, some small number
times the loss of say grammar,
plus some small number,
times the loss of like
sentiment analysis,
plus some small number, times
the loss of world knowledge,
plus--
and then all the way to, let's
say you have something times
the loss of math.
And so you can basically
write your overall loss
as the weighted sum of the
individual tasks in the data
set.
And now the question
is, let's say
I improve my loss
from four to three,
do each of these individual
tasks improve at the same rate?
Well, I would say, probably not.
So if you have a good
enough language model,
it's already doing
basically, perfectly
on grammar and
sentiment analysis,
so this might not improve.
So this might be saturated.
And maybe, the law-- the laws
on math is not saturated,
it's not that good at math yet,
so this could improve suddenly.
And I'll redraw the
diagram to show this.
So again, compute
here, and loss here,
and your overall
loss is like this.
What I'm saying
is, there might be
some part of that overall
loss that scales like this.
So this is say, grammar.
So for example, you could say,
if GPT-3.5 is there and GPT-4 is
there, you haven't actually
improved the grammar that much.
On the other hand, you might
have something like this,
for say, doing math
or a harder task,
where the difference between
GPT-3.5 and GPT-4 will be much
larger.
And it turns out you can look at
a big set of tasks, which I did,
and you can look at, what's the
shape of these scaling curves?
So I looked at 202 tasks.
There's this corpus called
Big Bench which has 200 tasks.
I looked at all of them and
here's the distribution.
So you have-- this was 29%
of tasks that were smooth.
So if I draw the scaling plot,
compute is on the x-axis,
and then here we have
accuracy instead of loss,
so higher is better, then
you have something like this.
I believe this was
22% will be flat.
So if you have your scaling
curve, it'll just all be 0,
the task was too hard.
2% will be something
called inverse scaling,
I'll talk about this in a sec.
But what that means is
the accuracy actually
gets worse as you increase the
size of the language model.
And then, I think, this was
13% will be not correlated.
So you have something
like that, I don't know.
And then finally, a
pretty big portion, 33%,
will be emergent abilities.
And what I mean by that is
if you plot your compute
and accuracy for a certain
point, up to a certain point,
your loss or your
accuracy will be 0,
and then the accuracy
suddenly starts to improve.
And so you can define
an emergent ability
basically as for small models.
The performance is 0, so it's
not present in this model.
And then for large models, you
have a much better than random
performance.
And the interesting
thing about this
is, let's say you had only
trained the small language
models up to that
point, you would
have predicted
that it would have
been impossible for the language
model to ever perform the task.
But actually when you
train the larger model,
the language model does learn to
perform the task, so in a sense
it's pretty unpredictable.
I'll talk about one final
thing, which is something called
inverse scaling/u-shaped
scaling.
OK, so I'll give a tricky
prompt to illustrate this.
So the tricky prompt is this.
Repeat after me.
All that glisters is not glib,
all that glisters is not--
and this is the prompt that
I give to the language model,
and the goal is to
predict this next word.
And obviously,
the correct answer
is glib because you
asked to repeat after me.
And what you see is, let's say
you have a extra small language
model, a small language model
and a large language model.
The performance for the
extra small language
model will be say here's 100%.
The small language model is
actually worse at this task,
so something like
something here.
And then the large
language model
again learns to do this task.
So how do we basically
explain a behavior
like this for a
prompt like this?
And the answer is,
you can decompose
this prompt into three subtasks
that are basically being done.
So the first sub task is,
can you repeat some text?
And if you draw the
plot here, again,
extra small, small large,
and then here is 100.
This is like a super easy task,
and so all the language models
have perfect
performance on that.
That's one hidden task.
The other task is,
can you fix a quote?
So the quote is supposed to be
all that glisters is not gold.
And so you can then plot, again,
extra small, small, large.
What's the ability
to fix that quote?
Well, the small language
model doesn't know the quote,
so it's going to get 0.
And then, the extra small
doesn't know the quote,
so it's going to get 0.
The small will be able to do
it, and the large can obviously
do it, so that's what the
scaling curve looks like.
And then finally,
you have the quote--
you have the task,
follow and instruction.
And obviously, this is
the instruction here.
And you can say, OK,
what's the performance
of these models on this task?
And the small model can't do
it, or the extra small model
can't do it, small
model also can't do it,
but the large model can do it,
so you get a curve like this.
And then why does this
explain this behavior here?
Well, the small-- the extra
small model, it can repeat,
it can't fix the quote, and it
can't follow the instruction,
so it actually gets it
correct, it says glib.
It says glib.
The small model can repeat.
It can fix the quote, but it
doesn't follow the instruction,
so it decides to fix the quote.
And then the large model,
it can do all three,
it can follow the instruction,
so it just repeats.
And so that's how if you look
at the individual subtasks,
you can explain the behavior
of some of these weird scaling
properties.
So I will conclude with one
general takeaway which is,
applicable if you do research.
And the takeaway is to
just plot scaling curves.
And I'll just give a
really simple example.
So let's say I do something
for my research project.
I fine tune a model on
some number of examples,
and I get this is my thing.
I get some performance there.
And then here's the
line of not doing
whatever my research project
is, and there's the performance.
The reason you want to plot a
scaling curve for this is like,
let's say you take
half the data,
and you find out that the
performance is actually here,
so your curve looks like this.
What this will tell
you is, you didn't
have to collect all the
data to do your thing.
And if you collect
more, you probably
won't see an improvement
in performance.
Another scenario would be
if you plotted that point
and it was there, then your
curve will look like this.
And potentially,
if you kept doing
more of whatever your
research project is,
you'd see an improvement
in performance.
And then finally,
maybe your point
is there, so your
curve looks like this.
And in this case
you would expect
to see an even larger
jump in performance
after you continue
doing your thing.
So yeah, I'll end
my talk here, and
happy to take a few questions
before Hyung Won's talk.
Yeah, go ahead.
So in your [INAUDIBLE] data
that has an operational source?
Did you write the data
based on the source?
Repeat the question.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, thanks.
Good question.
So the question is,
during pre-training,
how do you differentiate
between good data and bad data?
The question is or the
answer is, you don't really,
but you should by only
training on good data.
So like maybe you should
look at like your data source
and filter out some data if it's
not from a reliable data source.
Yeah.
Do you want to give us maybe the
intuition behind the intuition
for one or two of the
examples like emergent
or why tail knowledge
starts to develop,
sort of what's behind that?
What do you mean intuition
behind intuition?
So you've explained
intuitively these concepts
that you're seeing
in the graphs.
And from your experience and
expertise, what in the model
itself is really causing
that emergent behavior?
What do you mean in
the model itself?
Is it more depth,
more nodes, more--
Oh, I see.
--attention, in an intuitive
sense not in a [INAUDIBLE]??
Yeah.
OK.
So the question is
like what in the model
makes the language model better
at memorizing tail knowledge
or at doing math problems?
Yeah.
I think it's definitely related
to the size of the language
model.
So yeah.
If you have more layers,
you could encode probably
a more complex
function within that.
And then, I guess, if
you have more breadth,
you could probably encode like
more facts about the world.
And then if you want to repeat a
factor like retrieve something,
it'd probably be easier.
I'll get one more in person
and then I'll move this myself.
So when you were studying the
200-ish problems in the big
bench, you noticed
that 22% were flat.
But there's a possibility that
if you increase the compute even
further, you might have--
those might have turned out
to be emergent.
So my question to
you is that, when
you were looking at the 33%
that turned out to be emergent,
did you notice anything about
the loss in the flat portion
that suggested that they would
eventually become emergent?
Yeah.
I didn't notice anything.
Oh, sorry, let me
repeat the question.
The question is like, when
I looked at all the emergent
tasks, was there anything that
I noticed before the emergence
point in the loss that would
have hinted that it would
have become emergent later?
To me it was kind of tough,
we have a few plots of this.
You can look at the loss
and it kind of gets better,
and then suddenly it
spikes, and there's
like no way to predict
it, but also you
don't have perfect data
because like you might not
have all the intermediate
points for a given model size.
Yeah.
Great question.
We can just hang on.
We have a few online questions.
Online, OK, yeah.
We just have a few
questions from people
who are joining on Zoom.
The first one is,
what do you think
are the biggest bottlenecks for
current large language models?
Is it the quality of data,
the amount of compute,
or something else?
Yeah.
Great question.
I guess like if you go back to
the scaling laws paradigm, what
it says is that if you
increase the size of the data,
and the size of the
model, then you'd
expect to get a lot
better performance.
And I think, yeah,
we'll probably
try to keep increasing
those things.
Gotcha.
And then the last one.
What are your thoughts on
the paper if you've read it.
Are emergent abilities of
language large language models a
mirage?
Oh, yeah.
I always get this question.
I guess I would encourage
you to read the paper
and decide for yourself.
But yeah, I guess
what the paper says
is if you change the metric
a bit, it looks different.
But I would say, at
the end of the day,
I think, the language
model abilities are real.
And if you think
like, I guess, I
don't think that's
a mirage, so yeah.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
So thanks Jason for the
very insightful talk.
And now we have Hyung
Won give a talk.
So he's currently a
research scientist
at on the OpenAI ChatGPT team.
He has worked on various aspects
of large language models.
Things like pre-training,
instruction fine tuning,
reinforcement learning
with human feedback,
reasoning, and so forth.
And some of his notable works
include the scaling flan papers
such as FLAN-T5, as
well as Flan-PALM,
and T5X, the training framework
used to train the PALM language
model.
And before OpenAI, he
was at Google Brain,
and he received
his PhD from MIT.
So give a hand for Hyung Won.
[APPLAUSE]
Do we switch the slides?
All right.
My name is Hyung Won, and I'm
really happy to be here today.
And this week I was
thinking about--
by the way, is mic working fine?
Yeah.
So this week I thought about--
OK, I'm giving a lecture on
transformers at Stanford.
What should I talk about?
And I thought, OK, some of
you in this room and in Zoom
will actually go shape
the future of AI,
so maybe I should
talk about that.
It's a really important
goal and ambitious,
and we really have
to get it right.
So that could be a good
topic to think about.
And when we talk about
something into the future,
the best place to get an advice
is to look into the history.
And in particular, we'll
look at the early history
of transformer, and try to
learn many lessons from there.
And the goal will be to
develop a unified perspective
in which we can look into many
seemingly disjoint events.
And from that we
can probably hope
to project into the future
what might be coming.
And so that will be the
goal of this lecture,
and we'll look at some
of the architectures
of the transformers,
so let's get started.
Everyone I see is
saying, AI is so
advancing so fast that
it's so hard to keep up.
And it doesn't matter if you
have years of experience,
there are so many things
are coming out every week
that it's just hard to keep up.
And I do see many people
spend a lot of time and energy
catching up with this latest
developments, the cutting
edge and the newest thing,
and then not enough attention
goes into old things because
they become deprecated
and no longer relevant.
But I think it's
important, actually,
to look into that because
we really need to--
when things are moving so
fast beyond our ability
to catch up what we need to
do is study the change itself.
And that means we can look
back at the previous things,
and then look at
the current thing,
and try to map how we got
here, and from which we
can look into what where
we are heading towards.
So what does it mean to
study the change itself?
First, we need to identify
the dominant driving
forces behind the change.
So here dominant is
an important word
because typically, a change
has many, many driving forces,
and we only care
about the dominant one
because we're not trying
to get really accurate,
we just want to have the
sense of directionality.
Second, we need to understand
the driving force really well,
and then after
that we can predict
the future trajectory by rolling
out the driving force and so on.
And you heard that
right, I mentioned
about predicting
the future, this
is a computer science class not
like an astrology or something.
But we do--
I think it's actually not
that impossible to predict
some future trajectory of a
very narrow scientific domain.
And that endeavor
is really useful
to do because let's
say you do all these
and then make your prediction
accuracy to from 1% to 10%,
and then you make say 100
predictions, 10 of them
will be correct, say one of them
will be really, really correct.
Meaning it will have
an outside impact
that outweighs everything.
And I think that is
kind of how many--
I've seen many
general thing in life
that you really have to
be right a few times.
So why-- so if we think about
why predicting the future
is difficult or maybe even
think about the extreme case
where we can all
do the prediction
with perfect accuracy,
almost perfect accuracy.
So here, I'm going to do a very
simple experiment of dropping
this pen, and follow this
same three-step process.
So we're going to identify
the dominant driving force.
First of all, what
are the driving forces
acting on this pen?
Gravity downwards,
and is that all?
We also have say
air friction, right?
If I drop it, and that
will cause what's called
a drag force acting upwards.
And actually, depending on how
I drop this, the orientation,
the aerodynamic interaction
will be so complicated
that we don't currently have any
analytical way of modeling that.
We can do it with the CFD, the
computational fluid dynamics,
but it will be non-trivial.
So we can neglect that.
This is heavy enough
that gravity is probably
the only dominant force,
so we simplify the problem.
Second, do we understand
this dominant driving
force, which is gravity?
And we do because we have this
Newtonian mechanics, which
provides a reasonably
good model.
And then with that, we can
predict the future trajectory
of this pen.
And if we remember from
this dynamics class,
if we have this
initial velocity is 0,
I'm not going to
put any velocity.
And then let's say
position is 0 here,
and then 1/2 GT squared will
give a precise trajectory
of this pen as I drop this.
So if there is a driving force,
single driving force that we
really understand, it's
actually possible to predict
what's going to happen.
So then, why do we really fear
about predicting the future
in the most general sense?
And I argue that,
among many reasons,
the number of driving force, the
sheer number of dominant driving
forces acting on the general
prediction is so complicated
and their interaction creates
a complexity that we cannot
predict the most general sense.
So here is my cartoon
way of thinking
about the prediction of future.
x-axis, we have a number
of dominant driving forces,
y-axis we have a
prediction difficulty.
So on the left hand
side, we have a dropping
of pen it's a very simple case.
It's a difficulty
it's very small,
you just need to learn physics.
And then, as you add more stuff,
it just becomes impossible.
So how does this fit
into the AI research?
And you might think, OK, I see
all the time things are coming
in, we are bombarded
by new things,
and some people will come
up with the new agent,
new modality, new MMLU
score or whatever.
We just see so
many things it just
I'm not even able to catch
up with the latest thing,
how can I even hope to predict
the future of the AI research?
But I argue that
it's actually simpler
because there is
a dominant driving
force that is
governing a lot if any
if not all of the AI research.
And because of
that, I would like
to point out that, it's
actually closer to the left
than to the right than
we actually may perceive.
So what is the driving force?
Maybe before that, I
would like to caveat
that when I do
this kind of talk,
I would like to not focus too
much on the technical stuff
which you can probably do
better in your own time,
but rather I want to
share how I think.
And for that, I want to
share how my opinion as is,
and so it will be very
strongly opinionated.
And by no means I'm saying
this is correct or not,
I just wanted to
share my perspective.
So coming back to this
driving force for AI,
what is that dominant
driving force?
And here is a plot
from Rich Sutton.
And on the y-axis, we
have the calculations plot
if you pay $100, and how much
computing power do you get?
And it's in log scale.
And then x-axis, we have a
time of more than 100 years.
So this is actually
more than exponential.
And I don't know any trend that
is as strong and as long lasting
as this one.
So whenever I see this kind
of thing, I should say,
OK, I should not
compete with this.
And better, I should try to
leverage as much as possible.
And so what this means is, you
get 10x more compute every five
years if you spend the
same amount of dollar.
And so in other words, you
get the cost of compute
is going down exponentially.
And this associated
scaling is really
dominating the AI research, and
that is somewhat hard to take,
but that is, I think, really
important to think about.
So coming back to
this AI research,
how is this
exponentially cheaper
compute drive the AI research?
Let's think about the job
of the AI researchers.
It is to teach machines how to
think in a very general sense.
And one somewhat
unfortunately common approach
is, we think about how we teach
machine how we think we think.
So meaning, we
model how we think
and then try to incorporate
that into some kind
of mathematical
model and teach that.
And now, the question
is, do we understand how
we think at the very low level?
I don't think we do.
I have no idea what's going on.
So it's fundamentally
flawed in the sense
that we try to model something
that we have no idea about.
And what happens if we go
with this kind of approach
is that, it poses
a structure that
serves as a shortcut
in the short term,
and so you can maybe get
a paper or something.
But then it becomes
a bottleneck when--
because we don't know how this
will limit further scaling up.
More fundamentally
what this is doing
is, we are limiting
the degree of freedom
we are giving to the
machines, and that
will backfire at some point.
And this has been
going on for decades.
And bitter lesson is, I think
the single most important piece
of writing in AI.
And it says, this is
my wording by the way.
Say past 70 years of
entire AI research
can be summarized into
developing progressively more
general method with
weaker modeling
assumptions or inductive
biases, and add more data
and compute, in
other words scale up.
And that has been the recipe
of entire AI research, not
fancy things.
And if you think about
this, the models of 2000
is a lot more difficult
than what we use now.
And so it's much easier
to get into AI nowadays
from technical perspective.
So this is, I think, the
really the key information.
We have this compute cost
is going down exponentially,
and it's getting cheaper faster
than we are becoming a better
researcher.
So don't compete with that and
just try to leverage that as
much as possible, and
that is the driving force
that I wanted to identify.
And I'm not saying this
is the only driving force,
but this is the
dominant driving force,
so we can probably
neglect the other ones.
So here's a graphical
version of that.
x-axis we have a
compute, y-axis we have
a performance of some kind.
Let's think about some
general intelligence.
And let's look at two
different methods.
One, with more structure,
more modeling assumptions,
fancier math, whatever.
And then the other one
is a less structure.
What you see is typically, you
start with a better performance
when you have a
low compute regime,
and then but it plateaus
because of some kind
of structure backfiring.
And then with the less
structure because we
give a lot more
freedom to the model,
it doesn't work
in the beginning.
But then as we add more
compute, it starts working,
and then it gets better, we
call this more scalable method.
So does that mean we should
just go with the least
structure, most freedom
to the model possible way
from the get go?
And the answer
is, obviously, no.
Let's think about even
less structured case.
This red one here is, it
will pick up a lot later
and requires a lot more compute.
So it really depends
on where we are.
We cannot indefinitely wait
for the most general case.
And so let's think
about the case
where our compute situation
is at this dotted line.
If we're here, we should
choose this last structure
one as opposed to this
even less structure one
because the other one
doesn't really work
and the other one works.
But crucially, we
need to remember
that we are adding some
structure because we
don't have compute, so we
need to remove that later.
And so the difference
between these two methods
is that additional inductive
biases or structure we impose,
somewhat impose that
typically don't get removed.
So adding this.
What that means is
that, at the given
level of compute data
algorithmic development
and architecture
that we have, there's
like an optimal inductive
bias or structure
that we can add to the
problem to make the progress.
And that has been really how
we have made so much progress.
But these are like shortcuts
that hinder further scaling
later on, so we
have to remove them
later on when we have more
compute, better algorithm,
or whatever.
And as a community, we do
adding structure very well
and because there's an incentive
structure with like papers.
You add a nice one
then you get a paper.
But removing that doesn't
really get you much,
so that we don't really do that.
And I think we should
do a lot more of those.
So maybe another implication
of this bitter lesson
is that, because of this what
is better in the long-term
almost necessarily
looks worse now.
And this is quite
unique to AI research
because the AI research
of current paradigm
is learning based method.
Meaning that we are
giving models freedom,
the machines choose
how they learn.
So because we need to give
more freedom, it gives--
it's a more chaotic at the
beginning, so it doesn't work.
But then when it
started working,
we can put in more compute
and then it can be better,
so it's really important
to have this in mind.
So to summarize, we have
identified this dominant driving
force behind the AI
research, and that
is this exponentially
cheaper compute,
and associated scaling up.
Now, that we have identified
if you remember back
from my initial slides,
we-- the next step
is to understand this
driving force better.
And so that we're going to spend
most of the time doing that.
And for that, we need to go back
to some history of transformer
because this is a
transformers class
and analyze key
structures and decisions
that were made by the
researchers at the time,
and why they did that.
Whether that was an
optimal structure that
could have been
added at the time,
and why they might be irrelevant
now, and should we remove that?
And we'll go through some
of the practices of this.
And hopefully,
this will give you
some flavor of what scaling
research looks like.
So now, we'll go into a little
bit of the technical stuff, tech
transformer architecture,
there are some variants.
I'll talk about three of them.
First, is the
encoder-decoder, which
is the original transformer,
which has a little bit
more structure.
Second one is the encoder-only,
which is popularized by Bert.
And then third one
is decoder-only,
which you can think of it
as a current like GPT-3
or other language models,
this has a lot less structure
than the encoder-decoder.
So these are the three
types we'll go into detail.
Second, the encoder-only
is actually not
that useful in the
most general sense.
It still has some place,
but we will just briefly
go over that, and
then spend most
of the time comparing 1 and 3.
So one has more structure,
what's the implication of that
and so on?
So first of all, let's think
about what a transformer
is, just at a very high level.
Or first principles,
what is a transformer?
Is a sequence model.
And sequence model is has
an input of a sequence.
So sequence can be--
a sequence of elements
can be words, or
images, or whatever.
It's a very general concept.
In this particular example
I show you with the words,
sentence is a sequence of words.
And then we the first
step is to tokenize it
because we have to represent
this word in computers which
requires some kind
of encoding scheme,
so we just do it with a
fixed number of integers,
and then we have now a
sequence of integers.
And then the dominant
paradigm nowadays
is to represent each
sequence element
as a vector, dense
vector, because we
know how to multiply them well.
And then so we have a
sequence of vectors.
And finally, this sequence
model will do the following.
We just want to model the
interaction between sequence
elements.
And we do that by let them take
the dot product of each other.
And if the dot
product is high, we
can say semantically
they are more related
than the dot
products that is low,
and that's kind of
the sequence model.
And the transformer is a
particular type of sequence
model that uses what's called
attention to model this
interaction .
So let's get into the details
of this encoder-decoder, which
was the original transformer.
It's quite many, many pieces.
So let's go into a little
bit a piece at a time.
So starting with the encoder.
So here I'm going to
show you an example
of machine translation, which
used to be very cool thing.
And so you are-- you have an
English sentence that is good,
and then we're going to
translate it into German.
So first thing is to encode
this into a dense vector.
So here I'm representing
it with this a vector
of size three or something.
And then we have to let
them take the dot product.
So this lines
represent which element
can talk to which
element, other elements.
And here because
it's an input, we
take what is called a
bidirectional attention,
so any token can talk
to any other token.
And then we have this
MLP or feedforward
layer which is per token, it
doesn't have any interaction,
we just do some multiplication
just because we can do it.
And then that's one layer,
and we repeat that n times,
and that's just the
transformer encoder.
And at the end, what you get
is the sequence of vectors each
representing the sequence
element in this case a word.
So that's the output
of this encoder.
Now, let's look at
the decoder, which
is similarly shaped
stack of layers.
So here we put in as an input
what the answer should be.
So here, BOS, is the
beginning of sequence,
and then das ist gut, I don't
know how to pronounce it,
but that's the German
translation of, that is good.
And so we kind of go
through the similar process.
Here we have a causal
self-attention,
meaning that the tokens of time
step t can only attend to t
and before because when
we start generating it,
we don't have the future
tokens, so we cannot--
when we train it, we should
limit that, and that way,
this is done by like
masking, but this
is different from the encoder.
So after this, you can get--
after again, n layers, you
get this sequence output,
and you have this--
the output of sequence,
to sequence, to
sequence mapping,
this is a general
encoder-decoder architecture.
And when you get
this end of sequence,
you stop generating it.
So this is the overall picture.
Now, I'll point out some
important attention patterns.
So we are translating
into German what
is into input to the encoder.
So there has to be some
connection between the decoder
and the encoder that is
done by this cross attention
mechanism shown in this red,
which is just that each vector
representation of each
sequence in the output decoder
should attend to some of them in
the encoder, and that is done.
In particular the design
feature which is interesting
is that all the
layers in the decoder
attend to the final layer
output of the encoder,
and we'll come back to the
implication of this design.
So yeah, that's that.
And now, move on to the
second type of architecture,
which is encoder-only.
We'll spend a little
bit of time here.
So again, we have to--
we have the same input, and we
go through a similar structure.
And then in this case, the
final output is a single vector.
Regardless of the
length of the sequence,
we just get a single vector.
And that is that represent
the input sequence, that's
a dense vector representation.
And then let's say we do some
kind of a sentiment analysis,
we run through a task
specific linear layer
to map it to
classification label
positive or negative
probabilities here.
And that's required for all
these task specific cases.
And this is kind of
popularized by Bert.
And what this means is
that, here at the time,
2018, when Bert came out we
had the benchmark called glue,
which was a language
understanding task.
You have a sequence in
classification labels
out for most cases.
This was how the field
really advanced at the time.
So when we care
about such tasks,
then there's an
incentive to think
about simplifying
the problem, adding
the structure to the problem
so that we can make a progress.
So this, the
additional structure
that was put into this
particular architecture
is that we're going to
give up on the generation.
If we do that, it becomes
a lot simpler problem.
Instead of sequence to sequence,
we're talking about sequence
to classification labels, and
that's just so much easier.
And so at some point, 2018,
2019, a lot of the papers
are just research was
like, we sometimes
call it Bert engineers, a
little bit change of something
get like 0.5% better
on glue, and you get
a paper, and things like that.
It was very chaotic error, and--
but if we look at
from this perspective,
we are putting the sequence
structure of not generating
the sequence that puts a
lot of performance win,
but in the long term,
it's not really useful.
So we're not going to look at
this encoder-only architecture
going forward.
Third architecture,
decoder-only.
This one is my
favorite personally.
And it looks kind of daunting
because of this attention
pattern, but it
actually is very simple.
So here, we only
have a single stack,
and it can actually
generate stuff.
And so there's misconception
that some people think this
decoder-only architecture is
used for language modeling next
to prediction, so it cannot be
used for supervised learning.
But here, we can actually do it.
The trick is to have
this input that is good,
concatenate it with the target.
And if you do that,
then it just becomes
simple to sequence
in sequence out.
So what we do is, the
self-attention mechanism here
is actually handling
both the cross attention
between target and the input,
and self-attention sequence
learning within each.
So that's the causal attention.
And then as I mentioned,
the output is a sequence,
and then the key
design features are
self-attention is
serving both roles,
and we are in some sense sharing
the parameters between input
and target.
So same set of parameters
are applied to both input
and the target sequences.
So this is the
decoder only, now,
we will go into the comparison.
So I think there are many--
like they look very different,
at least, on the schematics.
So how different
are they actually?
And I argue that they're
actually quite similar.
And so to illustrate
that we're going
to transform starting from
this encoder-decoder which
has more structures
built in, and then
into the decoder-only
architecture
and see what are some
of the differences.
And then interpret
those differences,
those additional structures,
are they relevant nowadays now
that we have more compute
better algorithm and so on?
So let's have this
table, four differences
we'll see each of them.
And then as we go through,
we will populate this table.
So let's first look at this
additional cross-attention.
What that means is
that, this on the left
is an encoder-decoder, which
has this additional red block,
the cross-attention
compared to the simpler
one that doesn't have that.
So we want to make it, make
the left closer to the right,
so that means we need to either
get rid of it or something.
And attention mechanism has kind
of the four projection matrices,
and so self-attention and
cross attention actually
have the same number of
parameters, same shape,
so we can just share them.
So that's the first step,
share both of these,
and then it becomes
mostly the same mechanism.
And then so that's
the first difference
separate cross-attention
or self-attention
serving both roles.
Second difference is
the parameter sharing.
So what that means is
that, between the input
and the target,
encoder-decoder architecture
uses a separate parameters.
And decoder-only only
has a single stack
so it uses the shared parameter.
So if we want to make
the left close to right,
we want to share the encoder
parameters, so let's do that.
I just color this, so now,
they share the parameters.
Third difference is the target
to input attention pattern.
So we need to connect
the target to the input.
And how does that--
how is it done?
In the encoder-decoder case,
we had this cross attention.
And then in the decoder-only,
it's a per the self-attention
doing everything.
What the difference
is that we have
this every layer of the decoder
attending to the final layer
output of the encoder, whereas
if you think about this decoder
is actually per
layer, within layer
when we are decoding
the say word thus,
we are looking at the same layer
representation of the encoder,
and that's within
layer, and I think
this is the design feature.
So if we want to make
this close to that,
we have to bring back this
attention to each layer.
So now, layer 1 will be
attending to layer 1 of this.
And that's then finally,
the last difference
is the input attention.
I mentioned about this
bidirectional attention.
And because we have this
decoder only typically,
with the unidirectional
attention,
we need to make them
matching, so that's
the we can just get rid of it.
I just got rid of the
some of the arrows.
So then at this point,
these two architectures
are almost identical.
A little bit of difference
in the cross attention,
but same number of parameters.
And if you have
in deep learning,
if you just train these,
these two architecture
in the same task,
same data, I think,
you will get pretty much
within the noise, probably
closer than if you train
the same thing twice.
So I would say
they are identical.
And so these are the
main differences.
Now, we'll look at what are
the additional structures, what
they mean, it means.
So yeah.
That's the populated
table now, and then
so we can say that
encoder-decoder compared
to the decoder-only architecture
has these additional structures
inductive biases built in, so
let's go into each of them.
The first one is what
encoder-decoder tries added
as a structure is that, input
and the target sequences are
sufficiently different that we--
it will be useful to use a
separate parameters, that's
the assumption.
And so why is that a useful?
When can that
assumption be useful?
And one example is
machine translation.
Back when the transformer
was introduced in 2017,
translation was
really popular task,
and it was difficult,
considered difficult.
And because it's a
sequence-to-sequence
and you can actually
have a blue score which
is heuristic based
method that can give you
a single number and then
people can optimize that.
So what that in
that task, we have
this input and target in
completely different languages.
So if the goal is to
learn translation only,
then it kind of
makes sense to have,
OK, this parameter
in the encoder
will take care of the
English, and this parameter
in the decoder will take care of
the German, that seems natural.
And what about now?
Modern language models is
about learning knowledge.
And it's not just
about translation
or not even about
language, languages
comes up as a byproduct of
doing this next token prediction
and translation as well.
So does it make sense to
have a separate parameter
for this kind of situation now?
We have some
knowledge in German,
some knowledge in English,
and we-- if anything
we want to combine them.
And if we represent them
in a separate parameters,
I don't think that's natural.
So I would say with this much
more general, larger models that
can do a lot of
things, this assumption
seems very unnatural to me.
Second example is a
little bit more modern.
Two years ago when I was
at Google and with Jason,
we did this instruction
fine tuning work.
And what this is, is you take
the pre-trained model, and then
just fine tune on
academic data set,
and so that it can understand
the natural language
instruction.
So the detail doesn't
matter, but here
let's think about
the performance gain
by doing this fine tuning on
two different architectures we
tried.
So first five is
the Flan-T5, which
is T5 base which is the
encoder-decoder architecture.
Last one, the latter five
decoder-only architecture
based on PaLM.
So we spent 99% of the time on
PaLM, optimizing a lot of these,
and then at the end we just
spent like three days on T5.
But the performance gain
was a lot higher on this.
And I was really confused about
this, and in a very good way.
And after the paper
was published,
I wanted to take a little
bit deeper into why
this might be the case.
So my hypothesis is that,
it's about the length.
So academic data sets we
use, we use like 1,832 tasks.
And here they have this very
distinctive characteristic
where we have a long
input, long in order
to make the task more difficult.
But then we cannot make the
target long because if we do,
there's no way to create it, so
there's fundamental challenge
of that.
So what happens is, you
have a long text of input
and then short
text of the target.
And so this is kind of the
length distribution of what it
went into the Flan fine tuning.
So then you see this, you
have a very different sequence
going into the
encoder as an input,
and the very different type of
sequence going into the target.
So now, this
encoder-decoder architecture
has an assumption that they
will be very different.
That structure really
shines because of this.
It was a kind of an accident,
but that was, I think,
why this really architecture was
just suitable for fine tuning
with the academic data sets.
What about now?
Do we care about this
kind of assumption?
And if you think about the
general use cases of language
models nowadays, if anything
the more interesting cases
involve longer
generation, longer target.
Just because we
cannot grade them,
doesn't mean that we are
not interested in them.
Actually, if anything we
are more interested in that.
So now we have this
longer target situation,
so this separate sequence
length parameter doesn't
seem to make much sense.
And moreover, we
think about this chat
application like ChatGPT, we
do multi-turn conversation.
And then so what is
a target of this turn
becomes the input
of the next turn.
And then my question
is, does that
make sense to even think
about a different parameters
if next turn is going
to be the same thing?
So that was the first inductive
bias we just mentioned.
And then the second structure
is that, target element can only
attend to the fully encoded
ones, the final output
of the encoder.
Let's look at this additional
structure, what that means.
So as I mentioned, we have this
very top layer attending to it.
And so in deep neural
nets, typically, we
see that the bottom
layers and the top layers
encode information at
a very different level.
Meaning that, for example, in
computer vision, lower layer--
the bottom layers
encode something
like edges, top layers, higher
levels combining the features,
something like cat face.
And so we call
this deep learning
a hierarchical representation
learning method.
And so now the question is,
if decoder layer one attends
to encoder final
layer, which probably
has a very different
level of information,
is that some kind of an
information bottleneck
which actually motivated the
original attention mechanism?
And in practice I would say in
my experience doesn't really
make any difference, and that's
because my experience was
limited to say 25, 24
layers of encoder of T5.
So layer one attended
to 24, probably fine.
But what if we have 10x
or 1,000x more layers,
would that be problematic?
I'm not really
comfortable with that.
So I think this is
also unnecessary design
that maybe we need to revisit.
Final structure we're
going to talk about
is the, when we do this,
there's a bi-directional thing
in the encoder-decoder.
Let's think about that.
So yeah.
Bi-directional input attention,
is that really necessary?
So when we had this Bert, B in
Bert stands for bi-directional.
2018 when we were solving
like question answering squad,
actually it was
very difficult task.
So if you have any
additional trick,
it can make a huge difference.
Bidirectionality
was really useful,
I think, maybe boosting up
the squad score by like 20,
so it was really huge thing.
But at scale, I don't think
this matters that much.
This is my highly anecdotal
experience, so we did in Flan-2,
we tried both bi-directional
and uni-directional fine tuning,
didn't really make
much difference.
So but I want to point
out this bidirectionality,
actually bring in an
engineering challenge
for modern multi-turn
chat application.
So at every turn, the new
input has to be encoded.
Again, and for
uni-directional attention
it's much, much better, so
here is what I mean by that.
So let's think about this more
modern conversation between user
and assistant, how are you?
Bad, and why?
And so here, if we think
about the bi-directional case,
we will-- and when
we generate bad,
we need to encode this input
with the bi-directional thing,
which is fine.
And then after the
bad is generated,
when we're trying
to generate why,
we'll need to encode how, again,
because how can attend to bad,
so we need to do everything
from scratch again.
In contrast, if we do
uni-directional one,
we can do much, much better
because now when we are trying
to generate why, we don't have
to redo how because we cannot
attend to the future tokens, so
we don't have to do anything.
So if you see the difference,
this part can be cached
and then this part is
the only thing that
can has to be encoded again.
So this kind of makes
a big difference
when we think about
multiple turns going on.
So I would say, bi-directional
attention, that well, in 2018,
which is mostly sold
by scale, and now
because of this
engineering challenge,
we don't really need that.
So to conclude, we have looked
into this driving force,
dominant driving force
covering this research,
and that was this
exponentially cheaper compute
and associated scaling effort.
And so to understand
this driving force,
we analyzed some of the
additional structures
added to the encoder-decoder
compared to the decoder only,
and then thought
about how-- what that
means as a from the
perspective of scaling.
And I wanted to just
conclude with this remark.
So we have looked at these kind
of analysis, which are all--
one can say, this is
just historical artifacts
and doesn't matter.
But if you do many of these, now
you look at the current events.
You can hopefully think about
those in a more unified manner
and then see, OK, what
assumptions in my problem
that I need to revisit?
And are they relevant?
And if not, why?
And you have an answer to it.
Is can we do it with a more
general thing and scale up?
And so I hope you can
go back and really
think about these problems.
And together we can really
shape the future of AI
in a really nice
way, so that's it.
Thanks.
[APPLAUSE]
Hi, thank you for the talk.
So about the mix of
expert structure.
If your saying, what you're
saying is correct then
how long do you think
the mix of experts
is going to stay for the
new large language models?
So one thing I have to
apologize is the architecture
is kind of a thing that I'm
not really comfortable sharing
a lot, that's why I'm limiting
a little bit to the future.
So yeah, if you-- yeah, I'll
probably just skip that,
but I would say that
seems quite general.
So some of the changes
that you described
between encoder-decoder
versus decoder-only
like the parameter sharing and
the bidirectional attention.
Can they not be interpreted
as less structured or sorry,
more structured, or less
freedom for the model to learn?
Yeah.
I think one can do that, but
I think somewhat subjective.
But I think it's a simpler
structure that the model
kind of, if--
but we're just saying
like input and target are
just sequences and we just,
if we have enough capacity we
can just handle both.
And there are other
cases where like--
yeah, so-- yeah,
I can totally see.
Actually, maybe I should
have repeated the question.
The question is, can we think
about this parameter sharing
other structures in the
encoder-decoder as actually
less structure?
But I think it's a little
bit more complicated model,
and that such
complications of like it
has more assumption, right?
The input and target
are different.
I think that's a stronger
assumption than, OK,
this is a sequence.
We deal with the sequence
in a unified way,
so that would be just my take.
Do you have any thoughts
on the recent state space
models like mamba?
And how that fits into the
paradigm of less structure
and more structure,
without really [INAUDIBLE]
working on an AI.
Yeah.
OK.
It's hard to think
about it on the spot,
but I think there are to me, I
talked about this architecture,
but I don't--
architecture is kind of a it
doesn't change things too much,
and maybe it's a--
I think multi-modalities
might bring
in another challenges like when
this transformer structure might
become a bottleneck,
when we think about that.
But yeah.
So I think it's transformers
I've done a good job.
So maybe we should think
about it, especially
with the multi modalities.
So like for cross-attention
and casual attention
it's like imposing
permutation invariance
in a way for multi-head
attention instead of causal?
And then for computer
vision, there's
like a lot of learning
structure for invariances,
for self-supervised learning.
What do you think about
those in terms of complexity
that you talk about?
So the question is,
this causal attention
versus the
bidirectional attention.
They were probably fine
in the text domain,
but in the computer
vision case, that being
able to attend to the future
part of it is really important.
Yeah, is that the question?
But also, like [INAUDIBLE]
attention remove the invariants
for permutation?
So what do you think about
invariant like for observation
like you learn a lot of
invariance for augmentation?
So what do you think about
those as a way to structure?
So I think the--
I don't really like this
invariance and all these.
These are like how humans
think we perceive the vision.
CNN, for example, is like
translation invariance, which
was very important
we thought, but it's
I don't think it's
that important.
Actually, if anything now
it's hurting the model
learning more general thing.
And so the machines might
be learning the vision
in a completely different
way from how humans do,
and I don't think
that's problematic.
So those invariances, I think,
is like could be a good guiding
principle, but I don't--
I'm not too worried about just
not having such structures.
Yeah.
I'll just try out
like just based
on some metric if not having
the invariant structure
is actually better
and more scalable,
and I think that's probably
fine, and actually even better.
If we do it without the
structure it's actually better.
So I actually have
two questions.
One, so clearly,
you've been thinking
about how inductive
biases and structure limit
our potential essentially.
So I'm just curious, what are
some fake inductive biases
currently that you think
are big blocks that we
can release as or let go of?
That would be one
question to [INAUDIBLE]..
The current structure
that we should get rid of?
Just current
inductive biases you
think because clearly, you've
been thinking about this, right?
So when you look at the state of
research you must be thinking,
man, this is like a
pretty big inductive bias,
it'd be really cool if
we could let this go.
So I'm just trying
to see what you're--
Yeah.
So when I think about
this as an architecture,
I think, the
architectures are not
the current
bottleneck in my view,
and so partly because I did
a lot of the architecture
research.
And at the end, we published
this paper called, do--
like it's saying, OK, we
tried 60 different transformer
modifications, pretty much the
same thing, and none of them
really make sense,
make a huge difference.
Caveat with like now maybe the
conclusion can be different.
So I have a very huge bias
against like not doing
the architecture research.
And one message could be that,
actually, the architecture
is not the bottleneck
in further scaling.
And I think what's
the bottleneck now
is this learning
objective, especially
on the supervised
learning paradigm,
or even like self-supervised
pre-training.
What we're doing with
this maximum likelihood
estimation is, OK, given this,
this is the only correct target
and everything else is incorrect
because the probability measure
is finite.
So is that really a comfortable
thing to do teaching signal
to give the model?
And I think if we think
about the old days,
we were-- we have a-- we could
formalize the correct behavior
for a given input very well.
And maybe one answer being the
single correct answer is fine,
but now if we're thinking about
very general especially the chat
applications, OK, for
like write a poem,
and then you say this is
the only correct answer,
I think, that the implication
that could be really severe.
So I think that's
really something
that I'm not comfortable
with, and partly why
I'm interested in RLHF as one
instantiation of not using
this maximum likelihood,
instead using a reward
model as a learned
objective function, which
is a lot less structure,
now we can scale further.
RLHF itself is not really
that scalable, I would say,
but it just shows
that we can use
this supervised deep learning
to train a model that
serves as an objective
function, and that
really works in a cool way, I
think, that's a great paradigm.
Thank you.
Great answer.
Not that you're being
judged or anything.
But second question I
would say is, so then
in the beginning
of the talk, you
talk about the big driving force
to be the exponentially cheap
compute, right?
But some of the stuff
I've been reading
says Moore's law is
ending, and we're
going towards like
performance-oriented
architecture.
So can we rely then on--
right the past 50 years,
we had transistors doubling
or whatever, Moore's law,
but yeah, that's ending.
So when you talk about
the compute, these demands
that we've been looking at and
that structure our history,
we're also uncertain
as to about how that's
going to protect the future.
So what are some of
your thoughts on that?
Yeah.
I think the Moore's
law is really
a red herring in this
case because it's
like number of transistors,
but that doesn't really matter.
I think what matters is
the compute availability.
And like GPU, for example,
is a very different kind
of architecture,
and that enabled
the continuation of this trend.
And I think right
now 2023, 2024,
we're kind of
taking the shortcuts
with like low precision thing,
which still I think is cool,
but I think there are many
other GPU level things.
But also if we are kind of
sure about the architecture,
this is my thoughts, we can
like hard code into the chips
and that can provide
a lot of benefits.
And I think training
for training,
I don't think
that's really done.
But GPU, if you think about
it is like too general,
maybe that is like something
that we can revisit.
And so I'm not losing
hope, and I don't
see any trend of doing that.
But maybe other things
will come as a bottleneck
like maybe energy or something.
Yeah.
So physics probably is something
that we need to study again.
If you don't mind continuing.
But then the problem
is like, we're
talking about exponential
driving forces, right?
You can tell me that you
want to hard code chips,
but that's not the
same as telling me
that there's going
to be exponential
growth that we can
ride into paradise
or whatever the
hell we're going.
Yeah.
Here's my very boring answer.
I think, we just need to
do a little bit better.
And at some point, the
machines will be better than us
in thinking about chip design.
[LAUGHTER]
So I think it's half joking,
but if we look back at say
this video two years
from now, I think,
it will be less more of
a joke, serious thing.
Yeah.
Let's just get there first.
All right.
So thanks to Hyung Won
for an amazing talk.
[APPLAUSE]